Dorn McGrath Fairfax County and Loudoun County slide collection, 1963-2004
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Dorn McGrath Fairfax County and Loudoun County slide collection
1963-2004
C0210
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
0.5 linear feet (2 boxes)
The collection consists of 525 color slides that contain mostly aerial views of Fairfax County and Loudoun County, Virginia. The aerial views feature housing developments, automobile transportation corridors, Dulles International Airport, and the surrounding countryside.
McGrath, Dorn C., Jr.
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds a number of collections on Northern Virginia including many images of planning and development in Reston, Virginia.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Dorn McGrath in 2012 and 2013.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Arrangement
Organized by subject.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of 525 color slides that contain mostly aerial views of Fairfax County and Loudoun County, Virginia. The aerial views feature housing developments, automobile transportation corridors, Dulles International Airport, and the surrounding countryside. Many of the photographs at ground level feature the contested area at the intersection of Old Dominion Drive (Route 738) and Spring Hil Road (Route 684) that was the subject of a lawsuit between Mobil Oil and the Fairfax County government. In 1986 Mobil requested that the area be rezoned, and eventually succeeded after multiple appeals. There are also slides with charts and graphs, perhaps used for presentations. Some of the slides are individually identified with handwritten titles, and the titles follow the naming conventions used on the original slide boxes with some editing for clarification. The photographs of Loudoun County are mostly aerial photographs of Leesburg, Middleburg, and various interchanges in the county. There are several images of farms and the surrounding countryside.
Biographical Information
Dorn McGrath is Professor Emeritus of Urban and Regional Planning and Geography. In 2003 he retired from the George Washington University where he was founder of the Department of Urban and Regional Planning, Director of the Institute for Urban Development Research, Chairman of the Department of Geography and Regional Science, Professor of Urban and Regional Planning, and was one of the founders of the University's Graduate Program in Historic Preservation. McGrath also served as a member of the adjunct faculty at the Johns Hopkins University, School for Advanced International Studies. From 1987-1996 he served as Chairman of the Committee of 100 on the Federal City. Currently he serves as an adjunct faculty member of Goucher College.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Dulles International Airport--Photographs.
Geographical Names:
Fairfax County (Va.)--Photographs.; Loudoun County (Va.)--Photographs
Subjects:
Housing--Virginia--Fairfax County.; Planning--Virginia, Northern.
Document Types:
Aerial photographs.; Slides.
Contents List
- Fairfax County 1, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Page 1-2)
  21 slides.
- Fairfax County Water Tank, 1986 (Box 1, Page 2)
  4 slides
- New Communities and Airports (IAD), 1974-1998 (Box 1, Page 3-4)
  34 slides.
- IAD Environs, 1990 (Box 1, Page 5)
  19 slides.
- Fairfax Helicopter, Landfill, Tyson's Corner, 1986-1990 (Box 1, Page 6-7)
  23 slides.
- Thoburn, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Page 7)
  14 slides.
- Fairfax County (Chang), 1986-1987 (Box 1, Page 8)
  12 slides.
- Fairfax Helicopter, 1975-1990 (Box 1, Page 9-10)
  26 slides.
- Fairfax Mobil, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Page 11-12)
  36 slides.
- Mobil, 1986 (Box 1, Page 13-14)
  24 slides.
- Fairfax County Hazleton, 1987 (Box 1, Page 14)
- Fairfax County Pipestems, 1975-1990 (Box 1, Page 15)
- Local Plans Fairfax County, 1969-1975 (Box 1, Page 16)
  15 slides.
- Fairfax County, Hazleton, National Wildlife, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Page 17)
  18 slides.
- Fairfax County Miscellaneous, 1974-2002 (Box 1, Page 18-19)
  35 slides.
- Fairfax County 3, Fair Oaks, 1974-1997 (Box 1, Page 20-23)
  71 slides.
- Leesburg, Loudoun, 1970-1999 (Box 2, Page 1)
  14 slides
- Leesburg, May 1970, December 2000 (Box 2, Page 2)
- Loudoun County 1, 1988-2004 (Box 2, Page 3-4)
  25 slides
- Loudoun County 2, 1963-2002 (Box 2, Page 5-7)
  41 slides
- Loudoun County 3, 1970-2002 (Box 2, Page 8-10)
  45 slides